<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe declaration of the proceedings of the peace that is now intreating of betweene the King of Spaine, the Archduke, and the Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces together with an abstract of diuers weightie reasons and arguments alleged by the Netherlanders, to proue that the Generall States ought not by any meanes to grant vnto the discontinuance of their trade and trafficke into the East-Indies / translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08092</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22109014</idno>
  <idno type="VID">25094</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248515319</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 18455.3</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S1313</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08092)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25094)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe declaration of the proceedings of the peace that is now intreating of betweene the King of Spaine, the Archduke, and the Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces together with an abstract of diuers weightie reasons and arguments alleged by the Netherlanders, to proue that the Generall States ought not by any meanes to grant vnto the discontinuance of their trade and trafficke into the East-Indies / translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Philip Harison, and are to be solde at the little shop at the Exchange ouer against the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Spain.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Spain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  1516-1700.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  Commerce --  East Indies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25094:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25094:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE DECLARATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS of the Peace that is now intreating of <hi>betweene the King of</hi> SPAINE, <hi>the</hi> Archduke, <hi>and the Generall</hi> States of the Vnited <hi>Prouinces:</hi> Together with an Abstract of diuers weightie <hi>Reasons and Arguments alleged by the Netherlanders,</hi> to proue that the generall States ought not by any meanes to grant vnto the discontinuance of their trade and trafficke into the EAST-INDIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Translated out of Dutch into English.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Philip Harison,</hi> and are to be solde at the little shop at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> ouer against the Conduit. 1608.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:25094:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25094:2"/>
            <head>A briefe DECLARATION of the Proceedings of the Peace that is now intreating of betweene the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Archduke,</hi> and the <hi>Generall States of the Vnited Prouinces:</hi> Together with an abstract of diuers weighty Reasons and Arguments alledged by the Netherlanders, to proue that the <hi>Generall States</hi> ought not by any meanes to grant vnto the discontinuance of their trade and trafficke into the EAST-INDIES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irst, that it is most certaine, that friendship, conuersation, and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke, are necessarie appendances of true peace, according to the generall lawes of nature, of all nations, and of ech kinde of people, conuersation and trafficke being shewes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parances of friendship and true peace, which no man denieth or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuseth to grant vnto, but onely the enemie.</p>
            <p>Such an example was neuer found nor knowen, that euer any peace was made and agréed vpon, with condition that conuersation and mutuall trafficke should be debarred and forbidden, for that should be no peace, but a true and certaine banishment, which is neuer found to fall out but betwéene enemie and enemie.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Spaniards (alledging and conditioning
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25094:3"/>that we should leaue our trade and trafficke in the <hi>Indies</hi>) meaning is, that so by that meanes he might vse those of the Netherlands, that he should finde and take there, like banished enemies: for they would haue vs to kéepe the peace in <hi>India,</hi> and they would there make warre vpon vs, and we should be bound not to resist them.</p>
            <p>Which is a most sure and certaine token, that first sheweth an euident kinde of vnreasonablenesse and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice; and secondly a manifest deceit, by words and faire spéeches, offering vs a free soueraigne Estate, and in deed and effect would make vs much woorse then euer we were vnder our Princes, therewith saying, that wée desire peace, and in effect bring vs into a harder estate then euer we were during the warres, which is, that we should wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly banish our selues out of the Indies, that therein they might vse all kinde of hostilitie against vs; and that we should beare it patiently. Lastly, they shew foorth their old practises, which are, that they can not intreat of peace but with dissimulation, and that as then they are readiest to make warre.</p>
            <p>For that to alledge vnto vs (that must of force liue by the sea, and that are the best merchants and chiefest sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men in the whole world) that we should leaue off to vse our trafficke &amp; passage thorow the greatest part of the sea, and from the richest part of the whole trafficke of the world, is the shamefullest and vnreasonablest thing that euer man heard of, specially when as he séemeth to vsurpe that vpon other countries and kingdoms, ouer the which he hath no command, and ouer the sea where he can forbid no man to saile, the vse and passage whereof, <hi>(Iure genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um)</hi> is open and frée for all men, and whereof no man in the world hath any particular gouernment.</p>
            <p>This also should be an vndoubted and certaine ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw &amp; subuecsion of our Estate, which in this long and cruell warre, cannot continue nor prosper without frée trafficke by sea, it being the onely meanes, which God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25094:3"/>Almightie hath vsed for our vpholding and maintenance; and by consequence, as much as our trafficke by sea should lessen, according to the same proportion the power and strength of the land must of force be diminished, for that without it, our townes and inhabitants thereof, can not be maintained, much lesse can wée haue any publike aide by the rents and reuenues of the land, as other great countries and kingdomes haue, for our countrey is too small; but all our wealth and power must come out of the sea; and it is easily to be seene, for that as much of our aide as we should lose, if that we will leaue off our trade and trafficke in <hi>India,</hi> so much must we of force misse in our publike aide towards our maintenance.</p>
            <p>By the East <hi>India</hi> accounts and company it appéereth, that as now there are about <hi>40.</hi> ships there in <hi>India,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there are <hi>5000.</hi> sea-faring men, and that they are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue from thence at the least <hi>300.</hi> tunnes of gold, which is <hi>3000000.</hi> pounds starling.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Guyenna</hi> they trafficke yéerely with about <hi>20.</hi> ships, and <hi>400.</hi> men, and there they returne euery yéere about <hi>12.</hi> tunnes of gold, which is one hundred and twentie thousand pounds starling.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Puncto del Rey</hi> in the West <hi>Indies,</hi> they vse to trafficke with an hundred great ships, for salt, and with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>1800.</hi> men, which yéerely deale for fraught and salt, that costeth nothing but the fraught, and yet bring in ten hundred thousand Gulderns, which is one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pound starling.</p>
            <p>The trafficke for Hides to <hi>Cuba</hi> in <hi>Espagnola,</hi> vseth to maintaine <hi>20.</hi> ships yéerely, with <hi>1500.</hi> men, and there is yéerely ventured, not lesse then eight hundred thousand Gulderns, which is eighty thousand pound starling: which in all maketh <hi>180.</hi> ships, <hi>8700.</hi> men, and they returne <hi>413.</hi> times an hundred thousand Gulderns, which is <hi>4130000.</hi> pound starling.</p>
            <p>Which being compared with all the rest of our trafficke
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25094:4"/>and sea-faring, it will be found, that this doth farre sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe and exceede all our other trafficke and sea-faring, that we haue els where, both in stocke, number of well expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced sailers, and strength of shippes; and consequently that we leauing our <hi>Indian</hi> trade, should lessen and lose more then the halfe of our strength and power, not onely at sea, (without the which we can doe nothing) but also by land, for that all our might and power (for the reasons aforesaid) must come out of the sea.</p>
            <p>This being duly considered, it is cléerely and manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found, that although no merchants trafficks in other countries, and no man goeth to sea, but onely for his own profit and aduantage, that notwithstanding the publike State should be much more interested and hindered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, then the particular persons themselues: for besides this, that the publike State consisteth only of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie, and that they make the publike State, and that the saide publike State is strengthened &amp; becommeth mighty, according to the riches and wealth of the particularitie or Commons; yet it is most certaine that the particularitie can aid themselues without the publike State, but not the publike State without the particularity or Commons; for that particular persons going to inhabit in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, can from thence trafficke into <hi>India,</hi> as well as out of these countries, but the publike State must staie still at home, and behold it selfe lessened and much weakened in his forces, according to the diminishing of his trafficke, for that according to the proportion thereof, the number of the inhabitants decrease, and the force and power of the publike Estate weakeneth.</p>
            <p>Besides all this, consider that the sailers and sea-faring men, that are vsed by particular persons in trafficke by sea, are a mightie great number, that are maintained without any charge vnto the countrey, and daily practised and imploied at sea, that at all assaies and néedes they may be vsed for the aide and defence of the land, without the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25094:4"/>which it is impossible to haue any power at sea, as wée by experience see, that the mightiest kingdomes in the world haue no strength at sea, according to the proportion of their powers, but onely according to the proportion of the traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke that their countries haue.</p>
            <p>From hence it is well to be considered, that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard by great policie setteth this before our eies to intrap vs, offering vs the soueraigntie, that will affoord vs no more power, but onely a dignitie, as the golden fléece doth, which he vseth to giue vnto the nobilitie of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, for their vtter ruine and ouerthrow: and seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to haue vs in regard thereof to leaue off the greatest part of our trafficke and sea-faring, that we thereby being more then halfe weakened of our power, he might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter attaine vnto his cruell intent, and that he, after that, might without feare breake the peace, and take all aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages against vs.</p>
            <p>Which is most sure and euident by their owne professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For acknowledging that the Ring of <hi>Spaine</hi> onely ought to haue his <hi>Indies</hi> frée and vnmolested vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, hath mooued this offer of peace, &amp; desisting from his former pretences, so it is not to be doubted but that the same is the only meanes whereby he should be mooued to keepe the peace: for that according to the alteration of things, so the counsels and intents of Princes alter; spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially also for that héereby it is euidently perceiued, that this offer procéedeth not from good will and affection that he beareth vnto the peace, or that he is weary of the wars, but onely because hée feareth to lose his <hi>Indies,</hi> and that consequently it followeth that hée will beginne to make warre againe as soone as he shall once be released of that feare.</p>
            <p>Which shall be as soone as wée shall haue loft off our traffike to the <hi>Indies:</hi> for that once done, it is vnpossible for vs euer after to set it vp againe, the companie being once dissolued, the Merchants being in other Countries,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25094:5"/>and from thence traffiking thither, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> hauing cruelly reuenged themselues vpon the <hi>Indians</hi> that are our friends, and wee with our faithlesse leauing of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallen into hatred with the <hi>Indians,</hi> the matter would be vntecouerable.</p>
            <p>How could a more shamefull thing be heard of, than that we (that by the authoritie and commission of the States) which are confederate, by meanes of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, with the <hi>Indians,</hi> should abandonate them to the discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of so cruell an enemy, which they for our sakes, and vpon our promises, haue mooued against them: and that we should take from our Merchants and Sea-faring men (that haue so much offended the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that they may not abide to suffer them to come and traffike amongst them) the full traffike and dealing, that God, Nature, and the Lawes of all Nations giueth vnto them? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as to the contrarie we ought to shew them all the like fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as we in our néed and necessitie haue found at their hands, for that they with so great danger of their lines and goods, with the losse of so much blood, and by so many honourable and valiant actions, haue compelled the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> to this treatie of peace, and to acknowledge and confesse that it is they only that haue caused him to leaue off his pretences. Faith and fidelity do by no meanes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that wée should not seeke to mainteine the least and meanest of our Countrey men (which haue holpen, and put to their hands to support the common burthens and great charges of the land) in their estate and trafficke, and much lesse that we should hinder and cut off the trafficke of twenty thousand persons, which are participants in this treaty of peace; and so many expert and lustie seafaring men, that haue failed vnto the <hi>Indies,</hi> and such as perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture may finde more meanes to reuenge themselues vpon vs, than the Spaniards can.</p>
            <p>Our Forefathers in times past did take hard quarrels and warres in hand to maintaine their sea-faring and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25094:5"/>trafficke, which then was very small, and when as their whole stocke was not to be compared for value with the bare ships, with their furnitures that are in <hi>India,</hi> and wee being so mighty and strong at Sea, that the enemy thereby acknowledgeth himselfe to be constrained to abandon and leaue his own right, and desire &amp; seeke peace, should with our owne consents, suffer our selues to be banished out of the two third parts of the whole world, where he hath no command, and where we to the contrary are the strongest.</p>
            <p>We should buie this title farre too deare, for that in stead of being honoured thereby, it will bring vpon vs a great shame and contempt, not onely amongst our owne inhabitants, but specially out of the land, both amongst our friends and enemies. Our Inhabitants shall with good reason haue iust cause to be much offended thereat, to see that we abandon and forsake our traffick, and that they are compelled to withdraw themselues: our friends and allies will perswade themselues, that they are not to expect or repose any faith or fidelity in vs, when they shall see that we forsake our owne Country-men and the vnited <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that haue done vs so great good, and faith full seruice, to obtaine a bare title: and perceiuing vs to be so much weakened in our power at Sea, (which is the onely thing wherewith wée should haue the meanes to procure their good and to aid and assist them) would make no account of vs, so that we imbarking our selues in this ship of peace, vpon the assurance of our alliances, shall in the end finds our selues wholly deceiued.</p>
            <p>And by meanes of the aforesaid weakning of our forces we shall of our selues be the onely meanes to prouoke our ancient and Capitall enemie to breake the peace, and to make warre vpon vs againe.</p>
            <p>To allege that wée should bée content wich the like traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke and seafaring, as we had before the beginning of the warres, is no other thing, but that our enemie would gladly see vs in the like estate of small power and strength
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25094:6"/>as we were in at the beginning of the warres, and so the easilier to intrap vs: from whence God defend vs.</p>
            <p>It is also without any ground of reason, for that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though before the wars wée neither sailed, trafficked nor dealt in the <hi>Indies,</hi> yet we had both right and fréedome to haue done it, <hi>Iure gentium,</hi> which was by no man taken from vs: for the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> being Lord of those Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, had no lawful power in regard of his Spaniards, to take that from vs, for that by his oath, hée was bound to maintaine these Countries and the Inhabitants thereof in their fréedome of trade and trafficke, vnder the which, without all doubt, the full vse of the Sea, of the aire, and of trade and trafficke thorowout the whole World, was the chiefest thing: and doing otherwise he should haue dealt with vs cleane contrary to his oath: and there was neuer any mention or question made thereof that could be heard, till in the yeare of our Lord, <hi>1596.</hi> when the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards made an expresse Article thereof, in the transporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Netherlands vnto the Archduke, whereby the Archduke made himselfe (and not the Netherlands) seruile vnto the Spaniards; so that wée still remaine in the frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that we had before the beginning of the warres, the full sea-faring and trafficke of the whole World standeth open vnto vs, which but by warre and force cannot be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs.</p>
            <p>This proposition also is héereby manifested and made knowen, that they seeke by policie and deceit to deale with vs in this treatise of peace, for that the general States be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all by one consent fully resolued not to hearken vnto any treaty of peace, without they were first assured of the full and absolute fréedome of the Land, first desired to haue assurance vnder hand and seale, to shew that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> and the Archduke made promise to deale with vs, as with frée Countries, wherein they pretend not any right or title.</p>
            <p>And so entering into treaty, they would lay vpon vs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25094:6"/>the most vnwoorthie and shamefull seruitude, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was heard of. It is also expresly set downe and agréed that either partie should hold that which he now possesseth, vnlesse by common consent it were agréed to forsake any places that they hold; and now they will dispossesse vs of the most important possession that wée haue, which is, the possession and frée vse of two third parts of the Sea, and the whole World. They will take from vs the places and trafficke of the <hi>Indies,</hi> with the greatest halfe of our sea-faring and power at Sea, without giuing vs any places in stead thereof.</p>
            <p>To allege, that he in regard thereof forsaketh and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth his title and pretence vnto these Countries, which he by his letters hath promised to giue ouer: and further, that he would take nothing from vs, but by consent, and in exchange.</p>
            <p>That they would giue vs the traffike and trade in <hi>Spaine</hi> in regard therof, is but a vaine and méere toy. For that we haue alwaies had, and yet haue it at this present time, by meanes of other Countries, notwithstanding his interdiction: and when he should permit vs the frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome thereof, wée might well and fréely goe thither, for that there consisteth more therein than euery man marketh or perceiueth, for that thereby he obteineth his great customes. <hi>Spaine</hi> should be holpen by vs with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals in time of famine, and wée thereby shall put our stocke, men, ships and ordinance into his hands for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stage, therewith to master vs at his will and pleasure, as he meant therewith to haue ouerruled vs, and would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed haue ouerruled vs when he had his will, and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vs trade and traffike in those Countries, if wée had not taken the <hi>Indian</hi> traffike in hand: and we thereby shall vndoubtedly be ouerruled, and wholly ouerthrowen, it wée once leaue our trade and traffike in <hi>India,</hi> for that it would be vnpossible for vs to beginne it againe, for the reasons and causes before alleged.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:25094:7"/>
            <p> Lastly, if wée looke narrowly into this matter, we shall finde it to haue béene a thing altogether néedlesse to take warre in hand, and to consume so much blood and money for our fréedome, when we with our owne consent should make our selues seruile, and banished from the two third parts of the whole World. It was also néedlesse for vs to oppose our selues against the <hi>Spanish</hi> Tyrannie, if wee will subiect our selues vnder to Tyrannous a command, that we should not trade and traffike with all Nations, and also not with those that are not subiects vnto him. It was needlesse for vs to oppose our selues against the tenth penny (that would haue driuen all trade of Merchandise out of these Countries) when we seeke to giue ouer the two third parts, or the greatest halfe of our traffike and Sea-faring.</p>
            <p>The reasons and considerations that might yet be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alleged heerein are innumerable: but these seeme to be sufficient to conclude and prooue, that although we with all our hearts, good liking, truly, absolutely, generally, and vprightly desire a peace, yet wée desire not (vnder colour and pretence thereof) to be deceiued and beguiled, and to be brought into more and greater seruitude than euer we were before, but that we persist and continue in our aforesaid common resolution, and in the letters, and vnder the hands and seales of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Archduke, to deale in nothing else but for the maintenance of our fréedomes (together with holding all that which we presently possesse) without the which wée would neuer haue taken this treaty of peace in hand.</p>
            <p>Héerein neuerthelesse the aduerse partie should thereby be holpen, that peace should be made and agréed vpon in <hi>Europe,</hi> and that all the rest of the world should continue in warres, although the same is wholly contrary vnto the meaning of the generall States: which is no other but to establish an vpright sincere peace, friendship, mutuall conuersation, and traffike generally and without any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25094:7"/>he should neuerthelesse make no difficultie to lessen the warre in some part, and so farre as by consent were permitted vnto vs, and to appoint the limits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at his discretion, for that the same part that by his limits were excluded, should still continue in warres, and that with the offense and hurt that thereby might be done vnto the one or the other of the parties in <hi>Europe,</hi> the peace shall not be vnderstood to be broken: and that also for their sakes in <hi>Europe,</hi> within the appointed limits, no repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion shall be sought for, or may be taken.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>